[Music]
welcome to watch new in reporting for
finance sales and purchasing fixed
assets sustainability and maybe more
just like any good movie if you wait and
stay for the end credits you might be in
for a little bonus
surprise so let's dive into the first
topic which is Excel reports for Finance
in finance we have um made the Excel
reports that were in preview generally
available it's not only that we made
sure they worked but we also applied a
lot of new design and new things to the
layouts so here on the screen you can
see the seven different Excel reports
that are available for finance
everything from trial balance to
Consolidated trial balance if if you use
consolidation companies but also um
Collectibles receivables and payables um
so let me just show you one they look
kind of the same that's the idea that
the design should look and feel the same
so let's dive into HED accounts
receivables with the new Excel layouts
there are different ways to get to the
new Excel layouts in business Central
I'll show you a few the first is from
the business manager role center now I'm
in the Kronos demo company so there's a
little trick here if you minimize the
get started Banner here you find some
hidden menus and here you find Excel
reports if I expand this you can see um
the different or some of the different
reports available here I'll get back to
you what this Legacy part here mean but
we wanted to go go into aged accounts
receivables don't mind the preview it's
just my version
and um let's run the report as with all
the new reports you get teaching tips
both if it's enabled like here if you
choose the the title here you'll get the
teaching tip if you open the help Paine
you get the teaching tip there's also a
link for the report uh in documentation
actually let's just try to they do that
that's a Full Circle you can also read
more about the report and learn about
usage scenarios and so on so let's uh
get rid of this documentation page and
be back in B business Central and let me
run the the report since this is an
Excel report you just get the download
you don't get a print option here so
let's download uh and run the
report so it's downloaded let me open it
in
Excel and here in Excel we have some
security settings because because this
report uses power query we need to
enable it at least in my entro
organization and I need to enable the
content so these are security settings
as part of excel not something I can do
much about but this will load the data
into the report and um with all the new
Excel reports they follow a pattern that
I'll just demo with this and I then I
won't mention it in the other
demos each of the reports come with a
printable version so the first worksheet
here is each account's receivable print
this means if I actually print this
let's try
that you notice that the report fits a
page and that means you can also print
the the report in a nice layout let's go
back to the report and here instead of
printing we actually want to analyze
something because these Excel reports
are the the main reason we use Excel is
to have interactivity with pivot tables
and slices and so on so this particular
report has three different analytical
reports local currency by period foreign
currency and du by currencies let's
let's dive into the first
one so the bip period is uh you can see
here if I expand some of the of these uh
elements in a date hierarchy I I can
dive into uh into that I can also filter
with global Dimensions one and two so
Department code or customer group I can
simply use these slicers to filter into
whatever I like and with Excel I can
also dive into or sort or or filter uh
with with each of the columns here so
this is my accounts receivable by period
you also notice that we don't have the
report name because we wanted all of
this screen to be as much available for
analytics as
possible same type of report but now by
period in foreign currency so the same
type of navigation now you get the
currency codes um in this demo data I
just have US dollars but of course in if
you use foreign currency you would have
the different currency codes here and
the final report in a accounts
receivables is then your buy by
different currencies so you can see that
here in with the currency code of of US
dollar uh then if you have multiple of
these this will expand with different
currencies all the reports that are
provided by Microsoft have this about
the report worksheet now I have uh
hidden the environment name here the
company um is just our Kronos um and you
can see which user Rand the report
that's me me uh when when I ran the
report uh what the report was about and
here also just like in the help pain for
from the request page you can also go
back from Excel into the documentation
for this particular report and then read
more about
it so that's what we have for finance
and this is just one of of the finance
reports that is now generally available
in version 20 25 release Wave 1 within
the areas of sales and purchasing we
also made gen generally available two
new Excel reports or maybe four if you
if you also account for the or if you
think of the Aged account receivables or
payables reports as being in this area
they of course finan but they are
heavily relate to sales and purchasing
so there are two new reports here
customer top 10 and vendor top 10 and uh
let's just dive in uh to the vendor
report and see how that looks in
business Central so to navigate to the
vendor top 10 report you have options
you could use the Excel reports menu
here but we could also just tell me say
vendor top 10 and see if we can find the
new report so the vendor top 10 here is
the Excel report the vendor top 10 list
up here is the Legacy report that that
will be replicated so we'll want to
choose the new
one and uh I will just uh download the
report and open it in
Excel so the first worksheet is the
print worksheet here you get the
printable version of the top vendor
lists of course the number of vendors
chosen here is the filter you set on the
request page and then uh the second
worksheet sheet is the analysis
worksheet where you now have the slicers
for for filtering on or picking
different um different vendors you can
of course again uh similarly sort or
filter on vendor number or vendor name
and uh and get your uh vendor top 10
report this is a version of an Excel
layout that even have a visual which
means if I pick a few of these the pivot
table will change to that um and we have
the about report as well so that's the
vendor top 10 report in Excel but wait
there's more in sales and purchasing we
also gave you a little bonus it will
come in version 26. one two new queries
that allow you to slice and Di your
sales and purchasing orders in a more
flexible manner than what is possible in
earlier version so let's dive into
instead of purchasing let's dive into
sales and let's analyze some sales
orders so tell me I just search for
sales order per and here I get the sales
order performance analysis result let's
choose that and see what is possible or
what this
is so the teaching tip tells me this is
an query that joins data from sales
header to sales line what this means is
that I can start grouping my sales order
Lines by things that are on the on the
header so the first type of analysis
here is I can look at sell to customer
name I have three customers and now I
can see all the lines that are related
to this of course if I if I remove some
of these um data items I will not see as
much uh there so that's one way of
looking uh with the sales order
performance I can look across my
customers and see what I sold to them
your imagination has sets the boundaries
of the types of reports when you combine
header and lines into a pivot experience
like this one so go check it out when
the 26.1 release gets out and uh let's
see if you can not have one analysis but
maybe 10 different analysis tabs on this
query in fixed assets we made three of
the Excel reports or the three preview
report reports in Excel generally
available fixed assets analysis fixed
asset details and fixed asset projected
value I won't go and demo these because
they will look the same as what you have
seen before but of course now in the
context of fixed
assets as a bonus that you already have
in your environment today if you're on a
version 25.3 or later is similarly to
the sales order and purchase order
analysis we also added a fixed asset at
hoc analysis query that joins the fixed
asset um Ledger entries to uh to other
things such as fixed asset class subass
and things on the fixed asset card such
as depreciation book so that allows you
for a really really flexible analysis on
your fixed asset
transactions sustainability we added in
the last release wave through three
Excel reports so they have already
generally available but in this release
wave we also updated the layouts for
these reports to look and feel the same
as what you have um in in sales uh sorry
Finance everything you have seen until
now so um again I won't demo this but
you should go if you use sustainability
go and check out uh the new layouts for
the ex sustainability reports and start
using the new uh the new
layouts with all the modernization that
has been been done in the area of excel
reports and also the layouts that you
have seen we are also saying goodbye to
some Legacy Excel reports in the product
um and this these are the um I'll show
you how they look they will be present
in business Central for a few release
waves and then they will be removed from
the product so let's uh I'll just show
you where to find them so in case these
are the ones you use you should start
using uh the the more modern Excel
reports instead so in business Central
the Legacy Excel reports are the ones
you find under the Excel reports menu
and then they they now have a group
called Legacy where they're located so I
won't go more into details about that
but they have been moved to this group
and in a later release wave this group
will be removed and you can you should
only be able to find these in the RO
Explorer and then they will be removed
and we're also saying goodbye to some
old friends uh within Finance fixed
assets sales purchasing actually the one
the report areas where you have seen the
new modern generally available Excel
reports their counterparts from the past
have now been obsoleted and will be move
will be removed in a later version of
business Central for manufacturing
there's a full video on manufacturing
analytics and uh the modernization of
reporting in that area uh is even
greater than what you have seen in this
video so if you use manufacturing make
sure you watch the manufacturing
analytics video